<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine and true relation, of the going forth of a Holland fleete the eleuenth of Nouember 1623, to the coast of Brasile With the taking in of Saluedoe, and the chiefe occurrences falling out there, in the time of the Hollanders continuance therein. As also, the comming of the Spanish armado to Saluedoe, with the beleaguering of it ... And also, the base deliuery vp of the said towne ... Lastly, the reasons and motiues mouing the authour to the publishing thereof. ... By I.B. that hath ben an eye and eare-witnesse of this subiect.</title>
            <author>I. B., fl. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840182</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4658</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4658)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine and true relation, of the going forth of a Holland fleete the eleuenth of Nouember 1623, to the coast of Brasile With the taking in of Saluedoe, and the chiefe occurrences falling out there, in the time of the Hollanders continuance therein. As also, the comming of the Spanish armado to Saluedoe, with the beleaguering of it ... And also, the base deliuery vp of the said towne ... Lastly, the reasons and motiues mouing the authour to the publishing thereof. ... By I.B. that hath ben an eye and eare-witnesse of this subiect.</title>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1626.</author>
                  <author>Baers, Johannes, d. 1653, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By M.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Rotterdam [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Johannes Baers.</note>
                  <note>In fact printed in London? (STC).</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint "Printed at Rotterdam by I.B. 1626".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvador (Brazil) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:1"/>
            <p>A PLAINE AND TRVE RELATION, OF THE going forth of a Holland Fleete the eleuenth of Nouember 1623, to the Coaſt of <hi>Braſile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With</hi> The taking in of <hi>Saluedoe,</hi> and the chiefe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences falling out there, in the time of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> continuance therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo,</hi> The comming of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedoe,</hi> with the beleaguering of it, the accedints falling in the Towne the time of the beleaguering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And alſo,</hi> The baſe deliuery vp of the ſaid Towne by cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly Officers, with the great loſſe of honour and riches, and the hopefull expectation of a Princely Land: the excellencie thereof is truly (yet briefely) diſcouered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Reaſons and Motiues mouing the Authour to the publiſhing thereof.</p>
            <p>All which are briefely, truly, and plainely ſet downe, without fraude or fauour.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. B.</hi> that hath ben an eye and eare-witneſſe of this ſubject.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Rotterdam</hi> by <hi>M. S.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL ROBERT IOHNSON Alderman of the Honorable Citie of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Bermoda:</hi> and to that Honorable Company of <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda. I. B.</hi> vnfainedly wiſheth honor to your perſon and perſons, and floriſhing proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity to you in your affaires.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF not ouer bould, yet very bould I am, without your licence to ſhelter a weather beaten booke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your protection, being a ſtranger to you and remote from you, but thoſe which better know (then I) your readineſſe in the well acceptation of a weake mans willingneſſe, hath imbouldned mee to preſent it at your ſerucie, if it may bee ſeruiceable to you it hath it deſire, it requires no further wages: your wiſedome may finde what I aymed at, by the reading of it: you are in authoritie to make choiſe (with the reſt of the Honorable Companie) of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to bee remote in forraigne parts: behold as in a map the danger of diſcoragous, vnwiſe, yea fooliſh Officers: that ſo in thoſe great affaires you may haue (if you haue not) Officers that are wiſe, couragious,
<pb facs="tcp:4658:3"/>and feareing God, ſo ſhall proſperity bee to you, (maugure the power, malice, and treachery of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Enemies or home borne ſlaues: which may be feared, for reaſons which to ſome of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany I haue diſcouered, but now ſilence:) yet eaſily defeated, by wiſe, religious, and carefull Officers: and this will bee your wiſedome: ſuch wiſedome crowne all your affaires, ſo ſhall <hi>Barmodus</hi> be ſtill tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtiled <hi>Summer-Ilands,</hi> pleaſant and fruitfull to our Nation.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Rottardam</hi> 
                  <date>this 19 of Ianuary 1626.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A well willer to his Countrey and Countrey-men,</hi> I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:3"/>
            <head>To The Reader.</head>
            <p>EXſpecteſt thou from hence a matter beautified with Learned phrayſes, or adorned with Scholler like tearmes, thy expectation is fruſtrated: grapes may not be had from a thorny hedge. Reader, in this inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vollomne, the writer chiefely deſires to manifeſt the true proceedings of a matter not truly, not faithfully, nor yet not wiſely carried. The takeing in of <hi>Saluedoe</hi> in <hi>Braſile</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and the giuing of it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by vnderſtandleſse and cowardly Officers: a rumour of which hath ben hard of in all parts of Chriſtendome, and in particular in <hi>England.</hi> part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath ben truth, but another part vntruth; for parties in their owne caſes are commonly parſhall, as ſome in this thing hath ben: if an officer of <hi>Bay ſhould write of</hi> this matter, ſouldiers of the ſame place would ſay he writ to leſſon (if not to nullifie) officers faults and falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, if a ſouldier ſhould take in hand the diſcouery of all the proceedings in theſe affaires, preſently would the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders ſay, enuy (not loue to his Countrey) did ſtir him vp to write, what the ſouldiers would haue goe for truth, not what is truth indeed; if any ſhould write hereof that hath not ben eye witneſſe of all things that hath ben paſsed, he might vnwitingly and vnwillingly write contrary to the truth, I being not on officer in <hi>Saluedoe,</hi> let not any thinke I haue masked the matchleſſe baſeneſſe of theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: nor being a ſouldier I may not bee ſuſpected to haue drawne a curtaine before the condemned faults of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I haue not beene a ſtranger to theſe things, that any ſhould challenge me of ignorance, but I haue en an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all things from the going out of the Fleete from
<pb facs="tcp:4658:4"/>
               <hi>Taxſel</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> which went forth the <hi>13</hi> of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>1623,</hi> till our comming forth from Bay the <hi>18</hi> of Iuly <hi>1625.</hi> And further to take away all ſuſpition of dubble dealing in my proceedings concerning the officers, I doe vnfainedly acknowledge, that I haue ben aboue my cauling reſpected of all the officers, and moſt kindly and friendly vſed of them all, ſo ſmall is my hatred to them, that I could wiſh (with a prouiſo) that they were in the like hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red eſtate as I haue ſeene them in <hi>Saluadoe.</hi> Beloued Countreymen, I doe ass in the preſence of God intend to write the true proceedings of the Braſilian Voyage, not feareing the frownes or yet the fury of baſe officers: onely I deſire that all that reades will not be curious in prying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the manner of my writing, for I know it is faulty: I ſee it my ſelfe, how then may it appeare faulty to iudiſſiall iudgements: to goe to amend it will require as much time and paines as to make a new one: and if I ſhould ſo doe I ſhould ſtill make my apologie to excuſe my faults: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it is I ſend it forth, deſiring thee good Reader is beare with ſmall faults: and leaue the grater to my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, ſo I leaue thee to wiſdomes direction, and the Lords protection,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4658:4"/>
            <head>A PLAINE AND TRVE Relation of the going forth of a HOLLAND Fleete the leuenth of Nouember 1623, to the Coaſt of <hi>Braſile.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>BRaſile</hi> is a Continent ſo great and large that it is not yet by any wholly diſcouered, yet as by a patterne of ſtuffe or cloath the whole peice is knowne, ſo by the relation of part thereof you may gather what the whole is. The Land, namely thoſe parts which ye neere to the Bay, is a Land very fruitfull and healthfull. <hi>Saluadoe</hi> which is the name of the Towne, it lyeth in thirteene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; it is a Land that conſiſteth of hills and vallies, the hills are not ſo high, but the higheſt beares trees and fruite of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts, the vallies and plaine Land is not ſo low but that it auoids all waters, and brings forth graſſe, fruits, and hearbs in aboundance; the fruits of the Land as they are many for varietie, ſo is their aboundance of euery ſort, and generally they are pleaſant to eate, and very healthfull to the body; there are a numberleſſe number of Oranges and Lemons, the Oranges are generally ſweete (yet there bee ſome ſower) gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, like vnto a 2 penny loaſe, the Lemons are ordinary ſmal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r then the Lemons that come to <hi>England,</hi> yet they be of an excell nt relliſh and taſte, there bee alſo very many Plantings of two or three ſorts, they are called in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Bonantos,</hi> in one cluſter there grow ſome 250, there is alſo a fruite which wee call an apple, it is excellent againſt the bloody flux, which diſeaſe is ſubject to thoſe who diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elues with drinking of wine and eating of grapes, it cots like to a Pomgranet, Pomgranets there be many and extraordinary great, there bee alſo many other ſorts of fruits like to Cherries and Plummes, there is a fruite like in proportion to an Artichoke called <hi>Annanaſſes,</hi> it is twice ſo great, it hath the moſt excellent taſte in my iudgement of any fruite that is, at hath a little taſte like to a Strawbery, but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4658:5"/>far more ſauory, there bee alſo Pine Apples, Muskemillons, Potatoes, Water-millions, Cowcumbers, Radiſhes, and all ſorts of hearbs, and many ſorts of Howers, it bringeth forth a berry which is ſtronger in taſte then pepper, I am not able to call to minde the particulars of fruits which it brings forth, there be alſo many Grapes: ſome of theſe fruits are all the yeare to bee got, ſome three times a yeare, others twice a yeare, the Land hath very much cattill, as Bulls, Kine, Sheepe, and Swine. When as the Towne <hi>Saluades</hi> was giuen vp to the <hi>Spaniard</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> did victuall the <hi>Holanders,</hi> I did heare of credite (and I doe beleeue it) that one husbandman did ſe'l to <hi>Don Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derico</hi> Generall to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado 18000 Beefes, beſides Goates, Swine, and Sheepe, and of them there be great ſtore, alſo there be many Hens, Turkies, Peacockes, and other ſorts of ſmall fowles, there bee many wilde fowle, as Parrats and Perrecitos, the Land breeds many good Horſes, the <hi>Braſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> employ themſelues and their <hi>Negers</hi> chiefely to the planting of Sugar-canes and Tobacco, and to the making of both, the goodneſſe of both, and the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of both I need not relate of, for <hi>England</hi> hath good know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of both, the beſt Tobacco is but worth a Royall a pound, which is ſixe pence <hi>Engliſh.</hi> It hath plentie of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſorts of woods and rootes fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the vſe of Apothecaries and Dyers: the Land hath in it many great deepe and long Riuers of freſh water, in which R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uers there is a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of freſh fiſh, likewiſe the Sea runnes vp into the Land by cricks 40, 60, 100, mile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ſome places, within one daies ſaile there bee Townes and Villages thought to bee richer then <hi>Saluadoe.</hi> Some 140 miles from the Baye lyeth the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Dela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>plato,</hi> vhere there be mines very rich; one of <hi>Baye</hi> that was a ſlaue told me, that in that place there is not one in ten but hath their ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts and dores with lockes of ſiluer; by the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of reaſon and prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtion you may conceiue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that place may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> called the Riuer of Plate. Some three moneths after we had taken the Towne of <hi>Bare,</hi> there came a Shippe from that place which was taken price,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4658:5"/>that had in it all kind of kitchen veſſels of ſiluer.</p>
            <p>160. Leagues from <hi>Baye</hi> lyeth <hi>Fernaborke,</hi> by land it may be marched to in 25 daies as hath ben reported to mee, the Towne is not ſtrong on the Land ſide, but by Sea it hath three ſtrong Caſtles, hauing this but by report I will not further inſiſt vpon it.</p>
            <p>The people that are the naturall inhabitants thereof are the <hi>Braſillians,</hi> they which are now the chiefeſt are the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals.</hi> The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King clames Soueraigne, though by ſome denyed, and by the reſt vnwillingly acceped of. The <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillians</hi> are of complection tawny, of condition beaſtly, like vnto rauenous beaſts they will eate the bodies of dead men, and for that cauſe they are called men-eaters: ſome of them are brought vp to the profeſſion of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are a people very laborious, which is contrary to the deſire and diſpoſition of the <hi>Portugals</hi> and baſtard <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi> The <hi>Portugals</hi> which there inhabite are a people proud by nature, and haughtie in their carriage in time of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but in time of aduerſitie a flattering and crouching people, they are very idle people, deſirous to command but cannot endure to put a finger to worke, and that is one maine reaſon that makes <hi>Negars</hi> to bee ſo well ſold in that part, they are very curious in their apparell, and ſo in their diet, the women for daintineſſe may not ſet a foote on the ground, they muſt haue their <hi>Negars</hi> to carry them in Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chaires, the meaneſt of them in <hi>Emackos</hi> (yet I ſaw the time when they were glad to make vſe of their feete to ſaue their liues.) The Towne of <hi>Saluadoe</hi> had in it many whores, ſome of them being left behinde remained in the Towne all the time wee remained there, which was a ſnaire to our Commanders and a maine cauſe to the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence vs according to all hee did to the former adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people that were caſt out before vs; Theſe <hi>Portugals</hi> are partly <hi>Iewiſh</hi> partly <hi>Romiſh,</hi> and a great part of them are very A theiſts (hauing no outward reformation to any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.)</p>
            <p>This people hath had long peace, euery one ſitting vnder
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4658:6"/>his owne vine, hauing plenty of all things, but conſidered not from whence they enioyed them, they looked not to the giuer of them. But though they would not looke vp to God in way of thankfulneſſe and true obedience, yet God (after long forbearance did in iuſtice looke vpon them, their pride, their whoredome, their Sodome-like idleneſſe, and their <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolatrie (in ſteed of their prayers) hath peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the heauens, and did make way for the wrath of God to come vpon them which came vpon them ſodainly in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſtrocke feare and terrour to their hearts, and paleneſſe in their faces, diſtraction and deſperation in their mindes. A Nation out of the North came vpon them, a people whoſe language they vnderſtood not haſtily aſſaulted them, ſo that though their pots were on boyling, their <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars</hi> cooking, yea though their tables were couered, their wine drawne, yet had they no ſtomackes to eate, not harts to inui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the ſtrangers that were come vpon their Coaſt, yet thoſe ſtrangers fell a board hauing good ſtomackes, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the manners to ſtay till they were bidden, but it was likely the meate would haue ben cold had they ſtayed till they had beene inuited, for they were gon in haſt out of the Towne, but made no haſt to returne in againe, their haſt was ſuch that they left their Iewels, Rings, their Gold and Siluer behind them, yea ſome vnnaturall Mothers left their Children in their cradles. Behold and wonder: Behold for thy inſtruction, thou Land, Citie or Man, which art lifted vpon glory, what the Lord did vnto this people, the Lord gaue them riches, yea great riches, peace and plenty was in their borders, they had their harts deſire, ſo far as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they could haue.</p>
            <p>The M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rchandize of the <hi>Weſt-India</hi> was not wanting in her, the curious workes of <hi>Turkie</hi> was the adorning of their houſes, the fine cloaths of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> with Wine, Oyle, and Fiſh, and much fine flower was in her, the fine linnen and threed of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flauders</hi> was found in her, the Iewels of the Sea precious ſtones with the bones of Fiſhes and Beaſts were there, there was not wanting Muske,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4658:6"/>Siuet, Corall, Amber, Amber-greece, Pomander, in a word what Merchandize and commoditie that may be had in that honorable Citie of <hi>London,</hi> fit for the Nobilitie and Gentrie but was there for people of meane condition, I ſay the Lord did giue to them theſe and greater things in aboundance, but in that they ſpent them to pride, idolatrie and whoredome, and the ſatisfying of their fleſhly and wicked deſires, the Lord hath ſtript them naked and taken their glorie from them, puting them into the hands of an other people, our neighbour Nation <hi>Hollanders</hi> by name; I ſay the Lord put them into their hands, but they trampled them vnder feete, I doe not ſay the Lord gaue thoſe things to them, for the following Treatiſe will truely and plainely diſcouer, that for the <hi>Hollanders</hi> great abuſe of that great glorie the Lord put into their hands, the Lord tooke it againe out of their hands, and hath placed it in the power of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> but let the <hi>Spaniard</hi> take heede, the birde hath wings that is in their handes. So much for the diſcouery of <hi>Braſile,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I muſt acknowledge I haue ben much wanting, and on maruile. For firſt I haue not ben in the Land, becauſe wee were in a manner beleaguered all our being there. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe I had not the vſe of the <hi>Portugals</hi> tongue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I might haue made further enquirie. Thirdly, becauſe of an accident that fell out being homeward bound, I had my booke of remembrance taken out of my Cabbine by ſome as had no great loue to an <hi>Engliſh-man.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4658:7"/>
            <head>THE TAKEING AND LOOSING OF SALVADOR IN THE BAY, BY A FLEETE OF HOLLANDERS.</head>
            <p>THe leuenth of Nouember 1623, there was a Fleete of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> waied anchor at <hi>Taxell,</hi> pretending to goe for the <hi>Weſt-India,</hi> the Fleete was 25 ſhips in number, having a ſtrong wind there was ſome diſpertion of the Shiping, ſo that we loſt our Colonels ſhip, which came not to vs untill we had taken in the Towne of <hi>Saluado.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome moneths ſaile, we came to an Iland called <hi>S. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Iland,</hi> adioyning to <hi>S. Anthonies Iland,</hi> ſome 20 Leagues from the South Ilands, where the Fleete ſtayed 13 weekes, in which time there was diuerſe ſloopes made, this Iland hath an excellent Harbour &amp; there is very good watering. The Iland is very barren, yet it hath (as I geſſe ſome 20. thowſand <hi>Goates</hi> in it. The ſouldiers going on land, would catch ſome 400. at a time by compaſſing them in. I leaue this digreſſion. The Fleete waying Anchor made their courſe for <hi>Braſil,</hi> contrary to the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Souldiers. In twentie dayes the Fleete paſſed the line, and with a faire gale of wind diſcovered on Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the twentie of <hi>Aprill</hi> the coaſt of <hi>Brazil,</hi> where the ten Companyes of ſouldiers were put into foure Shipps. On Wedneſday we were ſeeking but could not find the Bay of <hi>Saluadoe.</hi> On Thurſday the 30. of <hi>April</hi> we found it, and with a faire wind we went into the Bay. At our comming in St. <hi>Anthonies</hi> Caſtell ſaluted the Admirall with two or three ſhott, who had the like gratulation from the Fleete. Where one of our Shippes did ſend a ſhott that uncapped the Caſtell. Before which Caſtell the Ships which had the Captaines and land ſouldiers anchored; the Admirall, the foure Ships did goe ſome two miles below the towne, the reſt of the Ships caſt Anchor before the towne, where wee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4658:7"/>were welcomed by the battery and Shippes of the townes who for two howers, did very manfully defend their place and diſcharge their peeces, but the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did ouer man them, and over match them, that within three houer, they had ſunke ſome eleven of their Ships and burnt ſome of them, the Vice Admirall himſelfe in a ſhallop went ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry boldly to the Fort, and he with his ſword and Piſtoll, ſet foote on the battery, upon which the <hi>Portugalls</hi> left the water ſide, and fled up into the towne, ſo that the ſea-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring men made plunder of the towne the ſame night.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſpace the ſouldiers were landed, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell made many ſhots at the floopes and boates of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, but not any was touched, notwithſtanding they made ſome fortie ſhots, but when a few of the Souldiers were landed, they fled and left their goods for their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. The armie marched to the towne without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption, we came before the towne about nine of the clocke at night, they made ſome 100. ſhot at our Armie, yet our ſouldiers made not any ſhot to them, but came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Port by the order of a guide, who did purpoſe to goe a backe way into the towne, when the enimy could do no good from the Port with their Muskets to our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe they were vnder the wall they caſt ſtones. The Leiftenant Colonell wheled the Army on, marching in a narrow lane, the enemy contrary to the expectation of the guid, had made a little breaſt worke: from whence they did play vpon our Army, at which inſtant their were killed the Leiftenant Colonel and a gentleman next to him, vpon the which the ſoldiers retreated, at their retreat there came out of a houſe by the gate ſome 30 Musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and made a vollie of ſhort at our ſouldiers, at which there fell an Engliſhman one <hi>Philip Rowlands</hi> and a Dutch Canoner, which Musketiers went into the Port, we being to my knowledge within fortie yardes of the gate, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Maior <hi>Scoutton</hi> commanded a Retreat to a Cloyſter, halfe a Musket ſhot from the towne, whereupon the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did lay downe their Armes, and went to Plander the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4658:8"/>out-houſes and Cloyſters, and finding much wine, halfe of the ſoldiers were drunke, and alſo ſome of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders lay ſcattering on the ground, but the enemyes not thinking how to doe any exployte on vs, tooke not advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thereat, but with all ſpeed in the night time made their flight from the towne, onely their remained ſome fortie ſoldiers with the Governour.</p>
            <p>At the breake of day there was Arme, Arme, all to their colours and places, intending to goe on the towne, the Captaines not knowing what the Shippes had done, nor what the towne had done, whileſt we were preparing for the making of an aſſault on the towne, the white flag from the towne was diſcovered, which was brought out to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Maior, who marched into the towne to the market place where all the Companies were drawne in batalio, and ſo commanded to ſeuerall parts of the towne, The Governour with ſome twentie more, with two Ieſuites: were preſently ſent priſoners into the Shipps. The ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers leaving their Armes, made boote of all things they could come to in the towne, where there was much ſpoile of breaking of Tables and Cheſts wherein there was much riches, and great ſpoyle of wine, ſo that I haue gone to the ancles in wine in cellars, I ſuppoſe that there was ſpoild, twentie thouſand pounds, which might haue ben well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by carefull Officers. I thinke that the valew that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Soldiers, and ſea-faring men got, was more in value then that which came into accompts for the Maſters of the Voyage, and yet it was cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dibly reported, that the bootie which was got then: was fiue Millions. Two dayes after the taking in of the towne, the Governour, the Colonell and the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi> came with his Ships and Slopes, who vnderſtanding that the towne of bay was taken in, he ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and tooke on mightily that he had loſt the honor of the day in not taking the towne himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Portugalls which were in the towne were kindly intreated, and their houſes and goods they poſſeſſe freely, all that came into the Towne had paſſes from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4658:8"/>they promiſing to vſe their beſt for the bringing in of the <hi>Portugals</hi> to traficke, but the <hi>Portugals</hi> had not ſooner obtained their end, namely the fetching out of their hid riches in the Towne, but they ſhewed themſelues treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; for ſome 26 daies after the Towne was taken in, two of the ſouldiers going into the Land were killed by the <hi>Portugals,</hi> the Colonell was much in cenſed thereat, and going out of the Towne he tooke fiue <hi>Portugals</hi> whom hee cauſed to be ſhot to death without the Towne.</p>
            <p>The ſame morning the Colonell with ſome twelue horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men went out of the Towne, with ſome twenty <hi>Negars</hi> and a ſquadron of men, the Colonell riding before ſome twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeards in a narrow path, and woods on both ſides, the <hi>Portugals</hi> lying in ambuſh got about the Colonell, a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> ſhot him in the breſt, and the <hi>Portugals</hi> puld him of his horſe, who kild him and cut of his head and other parts, the moſt of the horſemen &amp; ſouldiers retired to the Towne, yet an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> brought in his head, vpon which there was a great alarme, but nothing done worth the writing. In his place there was made Colonell Captaine <hi>Alden Soulton,</hi> his brother <hi>William Soulton</hi> was made Captaine Maior.</p>
            <p>Some ten daies after, the Admirall with two ſhips made his courſe for <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three daies after, the Vice-Admirall with ſeuen ſhippes 250 ſouldiers heſides ſaylours went for <hi>Angoly,</hi> which was a hart-ſmart to ſome, and a weakening to the Towne, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an encouragement to the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to heare of the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Towne.</p>
            <p>The ſame day their went alſo foure ſhippes to the Salt Ilands, and ſo for <hi>Holland.</hi> So that there was left in the Towne but foure men of warre, and ſome fiue ſmall ſhips beſides the prizes.</p>
            <p>Some fiue weekes after the Towne was taken in, there came in a ſhip into the <hi>Bay</hi> from <hi>Liſhorne</hi> which the Sloopes tooke, in it was Oyle and Flower, and other Merchandize.</p>
            <p>The ſame weeke there came two ſhips from <hi>Angolia</hi> with ſome 1200 <hi>Negars,</hi> they came among our ſhips before that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4658:9"/>they found the Towne was the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> the one yeilded and caſt anchor, the other loward his ſailes and made as if they would caſt anchor, but paſſing by our ſhippes into the Land-ward, hoyſed ſaile and away into the Land, our ſloopes and ſhippes followed her but came backe without her.</p>
            <p>The latter end of Iuly there came another ſhip from <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabuck,</hi> who making in, our ſloopes with a pinnace and ſhippe made out, ſhee ſuſpecting ſomething made out but the winde was againſt her, the ſloopes got to the wind of her and made fight, yet ſhe would not ſtricke ſaile, till the man of warre gaue her a ſhot, then ſhe ſtrucke, there was Tobacco and Sugar in her, with Siluer and other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities to a good value.</p>
            <p>The beginning of Auguſt there came another ſhippe in the morning amongſt ours, yet ſhe got away into the Land: It was reported by a <hi>Negar</hi> that came from the Enemie that the ſhippe had eight iron pieces and other munition, with wine and other prouiſion,</p>
            <p>About the twelfth of Auguſt 1624, there came a ſhip in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Bay,</hi> hauing a forewinde and ready to caſt anchor, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from vs boarded them, the Admirall of our ſhippes was in the ſloope (who now remaines with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the reaſon whereof I ſhall after ſhewe) hee comming into the Cabine found the Gouernour of <hi>Reginero Deplato,</hi> his wife and three daughters and two ſonnes in law, the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Captaine <hi>Cherk</hi> moſt badly went to ſearch the Ladies, which was very grieuous to the Gouernour, he told him in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> that there was no neede of that ſtraitneſſe, for there were chaines, iewells, and plate enough beſides. In which ſhippe all their pots and veſſells were of ſiluer. I my ſelfe had the weight of the veſſells of ſiluer which came to 150000 pound. Certainely it was a rich prize. The Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was well entertained, with his wife and daughters, one of them was thought to bee ouer kindly vſed, if it bee not true, yet the Colonell was much to be blamed for his priuate entertainment of ſome of them into his chamber, and in that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4658:9"/>he was truely condemned for a whoremaſter, for hee was not aſhamed to goe in the middle of the day to an open whore-houſe, which whore he cauſed to be married to a <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant or Factour, to whom hee gaue a horſe that hee might ride abroade whileſt hee had the key of the Factours houſe at home. This Colonell was alſo a great drunkard, his brother <hi>Williams Scoulton</hi> Maior, did diuerſe times reproue him for his wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>In September 1624 he ſent a partie of 25 ſouldiers and ſome <hi>Negars,</hi> to gather Plantings and Oranges for his whores two miles out of the Towne; their Commaunder was the Leiftenant to Captaine <hi>Iſanack</hi> with a Sariant of the ſame Companie, when they came to the place where the Oranges and Plantings were, the ſouldiers with the <hi>Negars</hi> left their armes on the ground and went vnto the trees, the <hi>Portugals</hi> comming on them with ſome 200, fell vpon them kild nine ſouldiers and the Leiftenant, tooke priſoners the Sariant with ſome <hi>Negars,</hi> the reſt went into the woods and hid themſelues: ſome of the <hi>Negars</hi> came into the Towne and made a great alarume, 200 went forth to relieue them, and did fetch of the nine dead men, but not the Leiftenant. Some ten daies after that, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came to a by-gard and kild two, and the reſt eſcaped into the woods.</p>
            <p>About the latter end of September 1624 Colonell <hi>Al. den Scoulton</hi> died ſodainly being much ſwolne with drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>The next day after, the Counſell made choiſe of <hi>William Scoulton</hi> for Colonell, and Captaine <hi>Kyfe</hi> for Maior.</p>
            <p>The former Colonell did ſhevv himſelfe more carefull in fortifying the Tovvne then his brother <hi>William Scoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton:</hi> for the former vvould yeald to aduiſe of thoſe vvho had better vnderſtanding then he in thoſe particulars, but this man would haue his words without counſell for Law though it were contrary to all reaſon: this man did much reproue his brother in his life time, for whoring and dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, and he himſelfe when he was Colonel, did farre
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4658:10"/>worſe in thoſe particulers.</p>
            <p>In October, their came a Ship of ſome 140. Tunne from <hi>Holland</hi> with a prize in it, it brought tidings that the Marchants of the <hi>Weſt India,</hi> had provided a great Fleete for our releife, and was readie to come out of <hi>Taxell.</hi> In the Chriſtmas holidayes, the Colonel with moſt of his Captaines &amp; Skippers, were for foure dayes together feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their foure men of Warre, and at every health, they had three peeces of Ordnance ſhot off out of every Ship, in thoſe foure dayes it was counted, there was ſhot off, 1600. ſhot by water and land, ſomewhat too much to be waſted eſpecially in that forraine land, the want of it was felt not long after.</p>
            <p>In three weekes after, there came three Shippes and each of them got a prize, they likewiſe brought tydings of the Fleete, there were alſo letters ſent that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleete would be at the <hi>(Bay)</hi> at the beginning of <hi>May;</hi> yet to my knowledge there was not any extraordinary mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of proviſion there.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Friday</hi> morning the 3. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> there were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſome 12. Shippes vpon the coaſt, but not diſcryed what they were, at 12. of the clock there was a rumour that they ſaw a 100, ſaile that the ſea was full of Shiping, all was in a maze, yet nothing done, at foure of the clocke their Fleete came to Anchor without the <hi>Bay</hi> ſome Leage to the North of S. <hi>Authonies</hi> Caſtell, then they were told to bee ſome 50 Shippes, there was great talke what Fleete it ſhould be, ſome ſaid it was the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> others the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saturday the 4 of <hi>April</hi> there came betimes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nine ſmall ſaile out of the land ward, who did paſſe our Shippes and ſo went to the Fleete, the ſloopes and Shippes might haue preuented that, but thy did not, what there reaſon was I know not, I gueſſe but I will not writ.</p>
            <p>About eleuen of the clock the ſame day, the Fleete way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anchor and came with a faire wind and tide into the <hi>bay,</hi> and caſt Anchor ſome mile from the Towne altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4658:10"/>then the doubt was reſolved, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> cullers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed that our enemyes were arrived, them might you haue ſeene palenes in faces, and amazement in moſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, ſuch were the diſtractions of them, that no ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die reſolution could be reſolved one, at this time wee had in our Harbor foure men of warre, two great Marchant Shippes, Sixe Youghts, three ſloopes, three fire ſhippes. We had Sailors and Soldiers ſome 2200. fit for to beare Armes, beſides ſome 700. <hi>Negers:</hi> It was thought by ſome, that had they ſent forth then their firie ſhippes with their Youghts, and ſloopes, they might haue made a good peece of ſervice on their enemyes, for we had a fare fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind and a darke Evening, and men fit and willing to haue gon on that ſervice, but the Colonel would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any ſuch thing. The next day, the enemy landed their Land-man: two miles from the Towne, and came marching within Musket ſhott of the Towne, yet our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander lay ſtill: onely they then beganne to fortifie the Towne. The ſame Sunday night, the Souldiers which were in the Caſtell ſome ſixe miles from the towme, came in a ſloope to the Towne: by the command of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, they made that haſt away, that they left fourteene dayes proviſion for 30. men behind them, power &amp; ſhot, foure peeces of Ordnance with divers Musketts, yet the Leiftenant was not blamed for it.</p>
            <p>On Monday the 6 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> the enemy did fall downe with his Shipping below the Towne, where they landed their bag and baggage, and the ſicke men with their Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Church-men. At Eleveen a clocke the ſame day there went out ſome 300. ſoldiers vnder the command of Captaine Maior <hi>Kife,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Hellman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> at which time we had taken from vs one <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, and their was killed one Dutch-man and a <hi>Scotch</hi>-man wounded, they were not out one houre but they came in againe, with many buffe coates, and gilt Rapiers and Ponyards, with the ſlaughter of many cheife commanders and ſoldiers,.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtable told me on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide (after
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4658:11"/>the Towne was deliueréd vp,) that in that out fall there were kild and wounded ſome 170, had they beene but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with 300 more out of the Towne, it had ben a good daies worke indeed.</p>
            <p>The Enemie after this was ſome ſixe dayes ſtill, onely their ſhippes now and then did make a ſhot, but our Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from the Forte did ſhoote them through and through, that made them way anchor and lay farther from the place.</p>
            <p>Some ten daies after they came to beſidge vs, they ſunke three peeces of Ordnance on the ſide of an hill to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vpon our ſhips, and hardly did they make a ſhot but they ſhot into the ſhips, where they kild and wounded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our ſaylours, yet they drew the ſhippes neare to the ſhoare, I could not conceiue nor cannot apprehend to what purpoſe they did leaue their Munition and prouiſion in their ſhippes, with ſome 250 ſaylours, whereas they could not doe any thing to the Enemie from their ſhippes, either by ſea or land; not long had the Enemie plaide at our ſhips but the Enemie had wounded and kild ſome 70 of our ſea-fayring-men, and brought to ground ſome ſoure of our ſmall ſhippes and the Admirall, to the great loſſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and Munition, then ſomewhat late they commanded the ſaylours to forſake the ſhippes, and in the night they got ſome of their Pieces with ſome of their prouiſion on land.</p>
            <p>Within 16 daies after the beleaguering, our people had planted on the ſea ſide in Forts and other places 36 pieces of Ordnance, they had 300 Muſqueters on the water ſide.</p>
            <p>The Enemie had planted againſt the Towne to the new Port ward called <hi>Iaſanaks</hi> Port three halfe Cannons, the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets was 28 and 36 pound, the firſt ſhot that did hit the new Port went through and through, it might haue been fitter called a baubell then a Port, fitter for banqueting then battering. The Towne lay ſo low, and the hills without ſo high, that the Enemie did not make Forts, but ſunke their Ordance in the gronud. The Enemie did begin to make a batterie neare to the ſame ſide of the Towne, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4658:11"/>Conſtable of <hi>Iaſanacks</hi> Port perceiuing the ſame, did make diuerſe ſhot (hee was an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi>) to the great diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Enemie, but the Colonell did come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him that he ſhould not ſhoote at all: the like was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the other Conſtables, to the wonder of all: all that was alledged by this Colonell was the want of Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it was true, how worthy of reproofe was he, that would waſt ſo much before in ieſting, as I haue noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but if there was Munition enough (as there was) I thinke there was iuſt ſuſpition of treacherie. The Enemie had within fiue daies placed in that batterie fiue halfe Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and preſently diſmounted our Ordnance on that ſide of the Towne, then they would but could not play with their Ordance, and when the Colonell was required to ſuffer to take ſacks of cotton and peeces of bayes to ſtop the the breaches that they might remount their Peices, hee would not yeald thereto.</p>
            <p>It was alſo reported that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Colonell had three ſeuerall Letters from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall, but there was on good proofe thereof, yet after the Towne was deliuered vp, the man that ſaid hee brought the Letters did teſtifie the truth of it, nominating the time and place, where and when hee met the Colonell: this I had from Captaine <hi>Deſhen</hi> one that was of the Counſell who is with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> now.</p>
            <p>It was likewiſe reported that the Colonel with two other Captaines, did intend to flie away in a ſmall Shippe.</p>
            <p>Some three weekes after the Leaguer, the enemy had planted nine Peeces of Ordnance at the other Port, and foure in another place, and fiue in another place, ſo that there was in all thirty ſeven halfe Cannons.</p>
            <p>Wee had mounted in the Towne 61. Peeces, but after the Enemy had mounted and planted their Ordnance, they diſmounted ours, ſo that we had not foure Peeces mounted, then they began to make new Fortes in the Towne, and <hi>blinds:</hi> vpon thoſe reports of the Colonel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue named, the Souldiers began to ſpeake and mutter many things againſt the Colonel, and Councell and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4658:12"/>The Souldiers reported, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir Captaines, nor Leiftenants, would not in the day time come in the works and tronches, It is ſome what credible, for they are like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Captaines, which were knowne by their rich at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, not by their wounds.</p>
            <p>The Souldiers ſome fiue dayes before the Towne was given over, went and complained to the Captaines that the Colonel was treacherous to the Towne, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that they would make another Colonel, and they would ſpend their liues in defence of the Towne, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſaid, they would kill him and make another of their owne choyſe, this was one Satturday morning the 25. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> at Eleven of the clocke on Satturday, there was a great alarum, ſo that we thought verely that they would haue made an aſſault on the Towne, we had kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and wounded in two houres ſome fourteene men. At the ſame time there was a Souldier, going to fill his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daleroes with Powder, he having his light match in his hand did fooliſhly ſett fire on the Powder, to the burning of ſome ſixteene men, ſome to death, all to great miſery, at two of the clocke the Alarum ceaſed, ſo that every man was commanded to his Colors.</p>
            <p>At foure of the Clocke, there went to the market place ſome fiftie ſouldiers (as they ſay) by ſome Captaines pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate aſſents, the Colonels ſeeing them marching towards him comes to them, demaunds the cauſe of their coming, one anſwered that they came to put out ſuch a treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fellow as he, and to make choiſe of one that would be faithfull: for their Maſter and for the Towne, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could reply (as I was told) one ſtruke him downe with his Musket, and other with their ſwords, but he got from them into the houſe wounded, the ſouldiers preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned to the Major Captaine <hi>Kyfe:</hi> and requyred of him to take the protection of the Towne, and them and they with all they ſouldiers would dy with him, he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame and promiſed the ſame.</p>
            <p>On Monday the 27 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> there was one from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4658:12"/>which called to the Centrie on the Port that they would ſend a Drumme forth, preſently it was told to the Colonel together with the Councell, who ſpeedily ſent forth a Drumme, when the Enemy ſaw the Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, they requyred the cauſe of the Drummes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming forth, it was anſwered becauſe they called for one, they replyed that they did not call, but ſeeing there was one come, hee was commanded to be brought to the generall, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned an anſwer to vs, that his Commiſſion was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and to put the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> to the Gallies, yet if they would ſeeke for mercy, he would in his owne Clemencie, giue vs all our liues; vpon this truce was taken for 6. houres, no ſooner was this noyſed, but that the Enemy came over their works, and brooke ſome pales downe, and the Souldiers on both ſides did ralke freindly together, two from the Enemy was let in blind-fold and led to the Colonel. There were conditons propounded on our part, but thought to great to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Enemy. Truce was continued for 24. hours, and two from our Captaines ſent to the Generall of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, others alſo came from the Enemy, in the meane time, I ſaw the Enemy working (contrary to order.)</p>
            <p>Truce was continued till Wedneſday. On Wedneſday, their went a ſouldier to the Councell, and told them that the ſouldiers did vnderſtand, they would not yeild vnto thoſe conditions the enemy propounded, ſo that it would be the loſſe of all their liues, for which reaſon he ſaid that the ſouldiers were purpoſed to giue vp the Towne, if they would not make compoſition, they thanked the ſouldier for his ſpeech, but did not enquyer from whom hee had heard the ſame conſpiracie.</p>
            <p>The Councell vpon this one mans ſpeech (and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon drunkard too) reſolved to deliuer vp the towne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any conditions, the Truce being continued againe till Thurſday, the Maior went to every Court of Gard: and demaunded whether the ſouldiers would be content with that agreement as the Councell ſhould determine off,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4658:13"/>which ſhould not be diſhonorable, they all aſſented to the ſame. Whereupon the conditions were agreed vpon, but not ſuch as the ſouldiers liked off for it was ordered that the ſouldiers ſhould the next morning goe to Shippe, and they ſhould either ſend their Armes before them to the Shipping, or they going before ſhould be ſent after aboard. Further it was agreed vpon, that the Towne with all the riches: ſhould be left there, and the Officers ſhould haue their Cheſts with wearing apparell onely, (I meane Captaines, Skippers, Preachers, Readers and Marchants) the reſt onely with their Knapſacks on their backs. The ſame night about fiue of the Clocke, there was let into on of the Ports: a ſquadron of the enemyes &amp; many Officers. The next morning, the Enemy came in at ſeven of the clocke in the morning, and our ſouldiers leaving their Armes in the market place, were commaunded downe to the water ſide.</p>
            <p>The ſame day being Friday the laſt of <hi>Aprill,</hi> there came the Enemy downe to the waters ſide in their Armes, their match light, and did march in the middeſt of vs. Such a ragged Regiment did I never ſee, halfe of them had no ſhoes to their feece, their Armes were like to them, ſome had halfe a Rapier, others had them tyed in match, not one in twentie, was in his full Armes fixe, they were lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſtrongeſt houſes at the waters ſide, where they kept their Courts of Gard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Frederico</hi> commanded vpon paine of death that there ſhould no wrong nor violence be offered to vs, which was carefully looked vnto by his Officers.</p>
            <p>Eight dayes after, there came a command that we ſhould goe aboard, ſo the ſeat chers came downe and the ſaylours were ſearched very ſtrictly to the ripping vp of their ſhoes and all ſuſpected places about them, this ſearch was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a day and a halfe, ſo that moſt of the ſaylors and a companie of ſouldiers were ſearched. But <hi>Don Frederico</hi> came downe to the water ſide, and gaue way that all the reſt of the ſouldiers ſhould to the ſhippes without ſearching.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4658:13"/>The fifteenth of May came the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Fleete before the Bay 34 in number, with their bloody colours. The next morning they came ſayling into the Bayes mouth. The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> ſeeing that, hoyſed ſaile, and with ſome 30 ſaile went forth towards them. The Admirall from the <hi>Spaniard</hi> made a ſhot at the <hi>Hollander,</hi> the Admirall from the <hi>Hollander</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him the like againe, and ſo went backe with the whole Fleete to ſea. At this time were the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhips much vnprouided, had the <hi>Hollander</hi> knowne ſo much I ſuppoſe they would haue come in and ouer-throwne the whole Fleete.</p>
            <p>There were many reports concerning that Fleete of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> but nothing ſo credible as for truth I will write.</p>
            <p>After we were put into the ſhips, ſome halfe Musket ſhot from the Towne, the Generall <hi>Don Frederico,</hi> did giue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that euery ſouldier of ours ſhould haue a pound of beefe a day, beſides wine and bread, for 2000 was this ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome giuen, but the neglect of moſt of our Officers was great, in ſomuch that many times for 3, 5, and 8 daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the ſouldiers ranſomes were neglected by them, they lying drinking on Land, and the poore ſouldiers famiſhing on ſhippe board, and this is the maine cauſe why our ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers came home ſo bare and naked, for they were forſt to ſell their apparell for daily prouiſion. They were put to ſuch a ſtraight, that they were forſt to ſwimme, and with pipes to fetch themſelues water to drinke, whileſt their Officers muſt haue the boates to attend them at their whore-houſes and wine-houſes. It is true that the Officers haue been taxt for this there, but they would excuſe it, but in truth they cannot, they be but meere excuſes. Our Enemies did much blame them for this thing: and worthy of blame they were.</p>
            <p>After the deliuering vp of the Towne we ſtaied thirteene weekes foure dayes in the Baye, and that was by <hi>Don Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derico</hi> his intreatie, as Captaine <hi>Franciſco</hi> told me; why <hi>Don Frederico</hi> did ſo, was, becauſe hee knew not where the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Fleete was, and hee ſeared leaſt wee going forth ſhould ioyne with them. In the meane time, they trimmed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4658:14"/>vp ſeauen of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſhips, and by intreatie (if not by command) got 250 ſaylors from vs, to manage their ſhips to <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the latter end of our being there victuals grew ſcarce, ſo that <hi>Don Frederico</hi> wiſhed that our ſhippes ſhould waite on him to <hi>Fernabocke,</hi> and there hee would bee liberall to vs. Friday the twenty-two of Iuly, wee with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do hoyſed ſaile. But let mee note one thing here which is worth the obſeruation, concerning the <hi>Portugals.</hi> The Prince <hi>Don Frederico</hi> a little before his goeing away ſold to the <hi>Portugals</hi> their houſes, which before were their owne, and at his goeing away did not onely take away all goods till it came to old ſtooles and dores, but alſo ſtript them na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of all Armes and Munition, and did take away all their Ordnance that was planted to ſea or land-ward. So that the Towne is novv more vveake then it vvas vvhen the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> tooke it in. More may be ſaid of this But I will not.</p>
            <p>We with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleete hoyſed ſayle (as I ſaid before,) the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleete was ſome 42 of their owne ſhips, &amp; leuen ſhips which they had of ours that they trimmed vp, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Samſon,</hi> the <hi>Tiger,</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ricke,</hi> the <hi>Gringe,</hi> King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Saul,</hi> and the <hi>Houſe,</hi> we had ſeuen ſhips but ſuch ſhips as n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y made ſuch a Voyage in, they had not beene trimmed in two yeares, they had no good tacklings at all, ſome of them had but an anchor a piece, they were all excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding leakey. In the ſhip that I my ſelfe came in, our ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers pumped 20 and 24 thouſand ſtrokes a day: our ſhip was courted the beſt, and yet ſuch it was, that mad the Skipper to ſay to me, that he couid wiſh himſelfe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to play croſſe and pile for his life. The prouiſion in our ſhips was ſmall, there was but for ten weekes, ſuch ſmall alowance as many could well haue eaten it vp in two dayes: their weekely ranſome was 4 pound of bread or veryua, halfe a pound of beeſe, 4 ordinary ſpoonfull of oyie, a quart or a pint of wine and a quart of water a day: let all men that reades or heares, iudge if our Officers w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not much faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty herein, or the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> if not both. Our Officers will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4658:14"/>not deny but that the Towne was delivered vp vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, but what conditions few knowes, baſe conditions all knowes. The ſouldiers diſarmed, left to the mercy of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> their Apparel., their vittals, and their goods, given to the Enemy, they put in ſhipps as captiues taken by the Enemy, and turned to the Sea: that if God had not extraordinary preſerued vs, wee had never ſeene our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Countrie. Nor to the <hi>Spanyard</hi> nor yet to our officers doe wee giue the prayſe of our ſafe arriuall, but vnto our good God. As all dew is, ſo doe we giue the ſoole honor and prayſe of our preſeruation, from all thoſe manifold dangers.</p>
            <p>One Friday night hauing a croſſe wind, we caſt Anker at the Bayes mouth, at which time foure of our 7. Shippes (in the night time) made away from the Fleete, the next day at Evening, the Admirall from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado wayed Anker with the reſt of the Fleete, and went into the Bay againe, with our 3 Shipps went in with them. On the next day at 6 in the Evening, there came command from <hi>Don Frederico,</hi> that Captaine <hi>Cherke,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Deſhene,</hi> ſhould goe into two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſhipps, the reaſon why it was thus commanded: was thought to be, becauſe the 4 ſhipps went away without the Generalls leaue, but I rather beleeved their was greater reaſons. For this Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Cherke</hi> did as I haue writ before, dealt very baſely in ſerching of the wife and daughters to the Governour of <hi>Regturo de Plato,</hi> then was the time or neuer for them to repay him his baſenes, the other Captaine was he that was our guide to the Countrey of <hi>Braſil</hi> and to the Towne of <hi>Saluedoe,</hi> for he was there three yeares priſoner as he told me, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> it may be thought, that ſuch a man was not for their profit to be returned to <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Munday morning the 25 of Iuly, the Admirall ſhot and wayed anchor, and we with them went out: ſome fiue daies wee kept with the Fleete, but in the night time the ſixth day we loſt (if it may be cald a loſſe) the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleete, which was bound for <hi>Fernabocke,</hi> ſo that wee made for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4658:15"/>and notwithſtanding the leaking of our ſhippes, the ſhortneſſe and ſcarceneſſe of our victualls, by Gods protection all our ſeuen ſhips came ſafe for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland:</hi> not looſeing 22 men in all our 1650 men. In that ſhip I was in we loſt but one, and that on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> coaſt, for which, all glory and praiſes be giuen to God, of vs which haue been ſo miraculouſly deliuered, and of all that wiſheth well vnto vs.</p>
            <p>If any enqnire or require a reaſon or reaſons why I haue cauſed to be publiſhed this ſmall booke, it might be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it is a booke of newes, and is not that a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon? But I anſwere, the maine reaſons which haue moued me to publiſh this booke are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt: By the earneſt perſwaſion of ſome Merchants of <hi>London</hi> and others, which in part heard the relation thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly: That the reading and conſideration of this might bee a motiue to all in authoritie that put men in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to beware of aduancing baſe minded men, men that regard goods more then God, their owne profit more then the honour of their Prince and Countries, eſpecially to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of aduancing ſuch into offices as reſpect not their owne credite, but will defaime their name by whoreing and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and beaſtly Boriſh carriages as was ſome, and a great ſome of their Officers. And this kinde of doings did ſo beſot them, that they became vnderſtandleſſe in theſe weightie affaires, (for I preſuppoſe that thoſe which choſe them ſawe ſomething in them worthy the choiſe.) I am fully perſwaded, had they beene ſuch comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as <hi>Iethroe</hi> had aduiſed <hi>Moyſes</hi> to make choiſe of, men that ſeared God, and men of courage, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing couetouſneſſe, <hi>Saluadoe</hi> had borne <hi>Orange</hi> colours this day; but theſe men feared not God, had they feared God, they would haue done as good <hi>Ezechiah</hi> did in time of danger, ſought to the Lord for helpe, not <hi>Saul</hi>-like to a Southſayer as did Colonel <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Scoulton</hi> with others, theſe men were ſo forre from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of couetouſneſſe that they loued couetouſneſſe; that is plaine, not onely by their ingroſſing of Gold, Chaines, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4658:15"/>Iewels in their cheſts, but in that they too vnworthy men gaue places of office for mony; and it is moſt plaine, and now euident, that they were not men of courage, by two or three witneſſes may a truth be affirmed, but I can bring forth two or ten hundred to confirme this, who haue been eye witneſſes of their cowardly carriages. But let that ſerue to proue this which is knowne of all, their baſe deliuery vp of the Towne: they had at their command 2000, beſides 600 <hi>Negars;</hi> this they cannot deny, for they receiued ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome after the Towne was giuen vp for ſo many.</p>
            <p>Let them plead for their baſenes as they will, and ſay they had not ammunition and proviſion, I partly knowe the contrary (by one of their ſecreet concell,) they had to ſerue for three moneths crediblie ſo reported, but a badge of their cowardlineſſe, was this their keeping of houſe, when they ſhould haue kept their works, and encouraged their Souldiers; If ſearch ſhould be made, you might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede find ſouldiers which haue loſt ſome their armes, ſome their eyes, ſome their legs, with other demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſouldiers of courage, but let all the Officers that came from <hi>Bay</hi> be ſearched: and one will not bee found (ſaue the Enginer <hi>M.Ioſe Middleburghe</hi>) to my knowledge that hath receiued there, any wound or ſcarre by their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. I will not deny but they may haue a wound, ſome of them which might bee receiued in the wine-houſe of the <hi>Portingals,</hi> after the Towne was giuen vp: but that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonſtrate their baſenes then their courage, their not comming into their works was a great occaſion to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the ſouldiers, for I did heare the ſouldiers much complaine of this very thing. How may <hi>Holland</hi> be grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that ſo great and Princely a thing fell into the hands of ſuch baſe cowardly Officers, double diſhoner haue they done, to that Noble Prince, &amp; Honorable States of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Lands,</hi> if they pay their liues for their great baſenes, what is that to ſo great loſſe? The beſt that can be made of this loſſe is to make choiſe of Officers for the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes as are men of vnderſtanding, fearing God, loving
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4658:16"/>the Honur of the Prince and Countrie, more regarding a good name and credite, then an evill reproach with life.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon of my writing is to ſet a looking glaſſe for baſe and cowardly Officers to looke in, wherein they may ſee their future ſhame and diſgrace, if they will perſiſt in ſuch wicked courſes, ſuch may ride on horſes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gold and ſcarlet to adorne their perſons, they may haue command of others, impriſoning &amp; hanging whom they will, but looke one our Captaines of <hi>Bay,</hi> they were ſuch; but what are they now? The day of accompt is come, they are in priſon, their honors is come downe, they would be (I thinke) now content to goe on foote, and all their comfort is now, they haue more mercifull Iudges then themſelues were, wherfore all that know your ſelues to be ſuch, in time captivate your baſenes, leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelues captivated your baſenes be diſcovered.</p>
            <p>The laſt Reaſon of my writing: and yet not the leaſt cauſe, is to publiſh to all (that will take notice) the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull works of God, in theſe particulars whereof I haue written, by the which wee may ſee Gods proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt a people. Theſe <hi>Portugalls</hi> had peace and plentie: aboundance of outward bleſſings, and theſe were conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to them for many yeares, but the abuſe of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: did provoke the Lord to anger, and though he did ſpare them long, yet they did not conſider it, &amp; layd it not to heart, &amp; turne from their wickednes, therefore the Lord tooke his owne cauſe in hand, and while they were ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing to their Netts, the Lord cetch them in his Nett. He ſent the <hi>Hollanders</hi> one them, who ſuddenly came againſt them, and laid their honor &amp; pride in the duſt. We were but a handfull in regard of them, it was reported they were in the Towne 9000. able to beare armes among them, and proviſion they had for 12. moneths. They had a batterie in the water for 9. peeces, ſome of which peeces wayed 41110 pound, they had beſids 8 Caſtels &amp; great Forts on the water ſide: they had ſome 70. Peeces of Ordnance in all, yet all could not help. God was againſt them, and they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4658:16"/>thought the whole world was come vpon them. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues they made report, that 10000 thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand was landed, whereas there was not landed 2300. God the Captaine of our hoaſt went before vs, who tooke a way from our enemyes all courage and boldnes, as he tooke off the Chariots wheeles of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hoaſt, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> before we had once compaſſed <hi>Saluadoe</hi> before our Trumpets did ſound, or our Drummes make an alarum, like <hi>Iericho</hi> to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> ſo <hi>Saluadoe</hi> to vs was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered vp. True was and is that ſaying which ſome hath ſaid, namely, that we tooke not in <hi>Saluadoe,</hi> but <hi>Saluadoe</hi> tooke vs in. Heere was Gods worke and it is worthy to be taken notice off: and to be had in everlaſting reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, it is good for Cities and Countries to take notice of this worke of God, take heed leaſt Pharaſaically you juſtifie your ſelues (without iuſt reaſon) and ſay you are not ſuch ſinners as they, leſt an ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dwriting come againſt you, &amp; the words be read, except you amend you ſhall likewiſe drinke of the cup of Gods wrath, which cup of trembling hath bin put into our hands: and we haue drunke deepe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And juſtly hath the Lord dealt with vs, he gaue vs (we got it not by our owne harme) honor, riches and victory, he tooke from our enemyes all their glory, and put it into our hands, but we haue trampled them vnder our feete. Our glory is become our ſhame, thougth we haue ben bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter taught then they, yet indeed we haue done worſe then they, they ſinned in curioſitie and daintineſſe of dyet, but we in glottonie and dronkenneſſe, if it could be we excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them in pride, the ſinne of whoredome, me thinks was more abominable in our time amongſt vs, then before amongſt our enemyes, for their religion giues a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in ſome caſes, ours not, they could haue pardons before the committing of it, but we by our conſcience &amp; the rule of God tells vs, that <hi>whoremongers ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen,</hi> without God giue repentance and pardon. And me thinks, the ſinne of our whore-maſters was the greater, in that they proſtrated themſelues to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4658:17"/>their captivated harlots, and to Heatheniſh <hi>Black-amores.</hi> I doubt I ſhould be tedious, if in each particular I ſhould make compariſon betwixt our enemyes ſins, and the ſins of our Army, onely this I will writ, that two things hath beene ſpeciall motiues to cauſe the Lord to be wrath with vs. Our not conſideration of Gods great iudgments on our Enemyes for their ſinnes, and our great vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes for ſo many, ſo rich &amp; vndeſerved favours beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on vs, well may it be ſayd to vs, that we haue bin a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and vnwiſe people, ſo evelly to requite the Lord our God, who gaue vs ſo many things and hopes of greater matters. While we be humbled for theſe things, let other people before warne to take due notice of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and his ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ritle on ſinfull people: and in time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, ſo ſhalt thou prevent a future repentance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhall not be thy ruine. In the laſt place, I bend my exhortation to all theſe, whom God hath giuen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glory and riches aboue their brethren; be ſure to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in thankfulneſſe to God, as God hath abounded in mercyes to you aboue others, thanks is the leaſt thou canſt returne to God, being the leaſt, if thou neglect it, me thinks it is one of the greateſt motiues, to ſtrip thee naked to thy ſhame, and diſgrace: and to make thee an enſample to others, as we that haue benin <hi>Saluadoe,</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to others.</p>
            <p>Let not any miſconſter my meaning, nor miſapply my writting, as if I ſhould writ in the diſgrace of <hi>Hollanders,</hi> our neighbour Nation and profeſſed friends, though it be true that moſt of the Commanders in this voyage were Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yet they were but few in regard of the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore iniuſtice it is to condemne a Nation for a few falſe perſons, and if we ſhould thus cenſure, we ſhold happily conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our ſelues. Lay the fault where it ought to be layd, and then drunkards, whore-maſters, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandleſſe perſons ſhall juſtly be condemned, not the fault leſſe Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4658:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
